<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://spyr1014.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://spyr1014.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-04T10:27:51+11:00</updated><id>http://spyr1014.github.io/</id><title>Andrew Jakubowicz</title><subtitle>Software Engineering Student</subtitle><entry><title>N-queens Problem Backtracking Animation</title><link href="http://spyr1014.github.io/nQueens-demo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="N-queens Problem Backtracking Animation" /><published>2016-09-25T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://spyr1014.github.io/nQueens-demo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://spyr1014.github.io/nQueens-demo/">&lt;p&gt;A visualization and explanation of how a backtracking algorithm searches for a solution to a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display:block; width:400px; height: 400px; margin:0 auto;&quot; id=&quot;canvas-nqueens&quot;&gt;
  &lt;canvas id=&quot;nQueens-canvas&quot;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;nQueens-n&quot;&gt;Number of Queens:&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input id=&quot;nQueens-n&quot; type=&quot;number&quot; /&gt;
&lt;button id=&quot;btn-submit&quot;&gt;Play Animation&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For performance reasons n is bound between 4 and 10.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Requires canvas supported browser. Tested on Chrome, Safari, Edge, Firefox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;n-queens-problem&quot;&gt;N-queens problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have a chessboard of width and length &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; where &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; is a number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; queens be placed so that none of the queens are attacking one another?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hbmeyer.de/backtrack/achtdamen/eight.htm&quot;&gt;Try it yourself here with 8 queens.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-would-the-algorithm-do-without-backtracking&quot;&gt;What would the algorithm do without backtracking?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without backtracking a program would place &lt;em&gt;all n queens&lt;/em&gt; before checking if any queens are attacking.
This leads to wasteful solutions such as an entire row of queens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t need a whole row full of queens before we know that the solution failed.
Instead we only need 2 queens to be attacking each other to know that the solution is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-backtracking&quot;&gt;Introducing backtracking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A backtracking algorithm is a way of computing a solution to a problem when constraints are known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The algorithm places one queen at a time.
If the queen placed is attacking another queen, the queen is removed and we try again in the next position.
This is the &lt;em&gt;backtracking&lt;/em&gt; step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see this in action. Run the animation and look for the queens being taken off the board.
This is obvious when solving for 10 queens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backtracking&quot;&gt;For more detail check out the wiki page on backtracking.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>A visualization and explanation of how a backtracking algorithm searches for a solution to a problem.</summary></entry><entry><title>A Taste of Programming with Pictures</title><link href="http://spyr1014.github.io/Hello-World/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Taste of Programming with Pictures" /><published>2016-08-28T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2016-08-28T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>http://spyr1014.github.io/Hello-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://spyr1014.github.io/Hello-World/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/p1/cat_and_mouse.png&quot; alt=&quot;cat and mouse on scene&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before reading this, install &lt;a href=&quot;https://download.racket-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Dr Racket&lt;/a&gt; and set the language to “Beginner Student”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-to-programming&quot;&gt;Introduction to programming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coding is a way to tell the computer what to do. Computers are very stupid, so we have to be very specific in the instructions we give. This little introduction will show you how easy it is to make a simple animation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;programming-basics&quot;&gt;Programming Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is a function! You already know a bunch of functions without even knowing you know. Plus is a function, and so is minus! So let’s see how these “functions” work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t already, open Dr Racket and set the language to “Beginning Student”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screen is divided into two sections. The bottom section has a little arrow “&amp;gt;” which you can type next to. This is a place where you can write code to be immediately read by the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type the following next to the arrow, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(+ 2 1)&lt;/code&gt; and press enter (make sure you include the brackets and spacing). You should get something similar to what’s shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (+ 2 1)
3
&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to guess how these work while you type them in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (+ 1 2 3)

&amp;gt; (- 10 2)

&amp;gt; (/ 6 2)

&amp;gt; (* 2 5)

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But computers are awesome and can do a lot more than just maths. Especially because people have written functions for us to use to do amazing things!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before drawing pictures, let’s write some code in the top window. This panel lets us write larger programs. This code only runs when we click the green run arrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type the following into the top area. Try to guess what’s going to happen when you click &lt;em&gt;Run&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(+ (- 5 2) 2 (* 5 (- 6 4)))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click &lt;em&gt;Step&lt;/em&gt; the code will execute step by step. This allows us to see exactly how the computer is reading the code. The computer moves from left to right, evaluating the contents of brackets whenever a closing bracket is encountered.
This is easier seen so I’ve written out the steps below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(+ (- 5 2) 2 (* 5 (- 6 4)))
(+ 3 2 (* 5 (- 6 4)))
(+ 3 2 (* 5 2))
(+ 3 2 10)
15
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it’s time for cats!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: If you ever want to look at a function in more detail. Click on the function name, and press &lt;em&gt;F1&lt;/em&gt;. This will open documentation for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-draw-some-pictures&quot;&gt;Let’s draw some pictures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very special kind of text editor. You can copy images into it!
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/p1/p1_little_cartoon_cat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Cartoon Cat&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/p1/p1_little_mouse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Small Mouse&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s put this cat into a scene!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing we must do is &lt;em&gt;import functions that let us draw&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the top window, as the first line of your code write the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(require 2htdp/image)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click run! Now you can use all sorts of fun image drawing functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the bottom panel lets try out some new functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (square 50 &quot;solid&quot; &quot;blue&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one lets us place images onto a scene.
Write it in the upper window and the press Run to see the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(place-image (circle 30 &quot;outline&quot; &quot;red&quot;)
             50
             50
             (empty-scene 100 100))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computer has to know where to draw the cat and the mouse. To do this the computer uses X and Y co-ordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top left corner of the screen has an X value of 0 and a Y value of 0. Travelling down the screen increases Y and travelling right increases X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.racket-lang.org/teachpack/2htdpimage.html#%28def._%28%28lib._2htdp%2Fimage..rkt%29._place-image%29%29&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;place-image&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; takes an image, an X and Y co-ordinate, and finally a drawing. This drawing can be another place-image function. This is how we will put our cat and mouse on the screen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(place-image &amp;lt;Image&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Xposition&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Yposition&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Image&amp;gt;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note that this template matches the way we used the function above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s define our cat and mouse images. This lets us use the word &lt;em&gt;CAT&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;MOUSE&lt;/em&gt; in the code to refer to the different pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type in all the code below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(define CAT &lt;img src=&quot;/images/p1/p1_little_cartoon_cat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Cartoon Cat&quot; /&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(define MOUSE &lt;img src=&quot;/images/p1/p1_little_mouse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Small Mouse&quot; /&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(place-image MOUSE 50 100
             (place-image CAT 100 70 (empty-scene 200 140)))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you run your code you should see your cat and mouse staring lovingly at each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/p1/cat_and_mouse.png&quot; alt=&quot;cat and mouse on scene&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not quite animated yet, but we’ve done almost all the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that we define CAT with the image of a cat, using another function called &lt;em&gt;define&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Have you noticed that Racket functions take a general form: (function-name input1 input2 input3 …)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;functions-bring-life&quot;&gt;Functions bring life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to write our own function. Not a boring function like &lt;em&gt;plus&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;minus&lt;/em&gt; but a cool function that draws a cat and a mouse in the right positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve actually done most of the work. All we need to do now is make the mouse move across the screen. If you play with the code you should notice you can change numbers to move the mouse around the screen. We’ll focus on just changing the X value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s modify the code to turn it into a function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(define (draw-cat-mouse-scene x-mouse)
  (place-image MOUSE x-mouse 100
               (place-image CAT 100 70 (empty-scene 200 140))))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have given our block of code a name. The name we gave it is &lt;em&gt;“draw-cat-mouse-scene”&lt;/em&gt;. We also gave it a single argument &lt;em&gt;“x-mouse”&lt;/em&gt;.
Notice that within the code we changed the X position of the mouse to the &lt;em&gt;“x-mouse”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you press Run, nothing should happen. However you can now type the following into the bottom window:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (draw-cat-mouse-scene 30)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will draw the scene with the mouse at an X position of 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally we can use a magic function to make the mouse move!
Add the following to the top of your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(require 2htdp/universe)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the program. In the bottom window you can now type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(animate draw-cat-mouse-scene)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;animate&lt;/em&gt; is a function that takes any function you give it, and inputs a frame number. Starting from 0 and increasing as long as your animation keeps playing. You’ll notice when you close the window a number appears. That number is the number of frames that your animation ran for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are abusing the fact that the mouse starts at an X position 0, and moves in an increasing x direction. This allows us to use the frame number to move the mouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cartoon animals gathered from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cliparts.co/clipart/3608707&quot;&gt;Cat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cliparts.co/clipart/5908&quot;&gt;Mouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><summary></summary></entry></feed>
